Hiram Putnam Papers, 1780-1885
Mortimer Rare Book Room, William Allan Neilson Library, Smith College
Hiram Putnam Papers
1780-1885
Putnam, Hiram
56
2 boxes (1 linear ft.)
Mortimer Rare Book Room Smith College Northampton, MA
The papers of Hiram Putnam and his wife Elizabeth Osgood. Includes correspondence, bills of lading related to the China trade (1823-1829) and other business documents; account books; and letters relating to his business and political interests in Syracuse, NY, especially those related to the public schools. There is also correspondence related to Dudley Post Phelps of a personal and religious nature and his poetry; copies of The Phelps record (Syracuse, N.Y., 1885), a genealogy of the Phelps family; and correspondence to Samuel Holten, related to the U.S. Continental Congress from John Avery, James Lovell and Azor Orne.
Hiram Putnam was born in Danvers, Mass., on Jan. 30, 1786. He went to sea in 1802 and by 1812 was a ship's captain. He was involved with trade to European and South American ports, as well as with the China trade, until 1827. This included time on the ships Aurora and Rising Empire, and for ten years he was the captain of the ship China, of Salem, owned by Joseph Peabody. Capt. Putnam married Elizabeth Osgood in 1816, the daughter of Dr. George Osgood, of Andover, Mass. There were five children born to this marriage.
The Putnams moved to Syracuse, N.Y. in 1829, where Mr. Putnam was involved with business ventures and civic positions. From 1833-1846 he was in partnership with Thomas B. Fitch in the wholesale and retail drug business. Together these two men also engaged in real estate ventures and brought some 220 acres of land into the city limits of Syracuse. He was also involved with banking interests. Mr. Putnam served on various town boards and was instrumental in developing public education in Syracuse. He also was involved with anti-slavery groups and the underground railroad. In 1838 Mr. Putnam helped in forming the Syracuse Unitarian Society and in the founding of the Church of the Messiah (later re-named the May Memorial Unitarian and Universalist Society). The 1885 church building (now demolished) contained a memorial window to Hiram Putnam.
Elizabeth Putnam died on July 28, 1848. At that time three children were alive: Charles H., who lived in Michigan; E. Augustus, who lived in Syracuse; and Lucy Blythe, who was married to Dudley Post Phelps and also lived in Syracuse. Mr. Putnam lived with the Phelps in his later years and died in their home on Nov. 8, 1874.
Lucy Blythe Putnam (born in Salem, Mass., June 4, 1826) married Dudley Post Phelps on Sep. 3, 1845 in Syracuse. Mr. Phelps was born at Preble, N.Y., Oct. 8, 1817. He was by training an attorney, but was largely involved with the Syracuse and Utica Railroad from the early 1840s until the spring of 1852. From April 1856 to May 1860 he was involved with the Michigan Southern and Northern Indiana Railroad Company and from 1861 to 1878 was employed in various banking establishments in Syracuse. In addition, Mr. Phelps served on various civic boards. He died on Sep. 25, 1880. Lucy Blythe died June 17, 1907 at Cazenovia, N.Y.
The papers of Hiram Putnam and his wife Elizabeth Osgood include their correspondence, bills of lading related to the South American and China trade (1823-1829) and other business documents. There are account books, including one that has accounts and letter book from Putnam's time on the high seas (1813-1816). Some letters relate to his business and political interests in Syracuse, NY, especially those related to the public schools.
There is correspondence related to Dudley Post Phelps of a personal and religious nature (relative to the true nature of Jesus Christ) and his poetry. There are also annotated copies of his: The Phelps record (Syracuse, N.Y., 1885), a genealogy of the Phelps family.
In addition, there is correspondence received by Samuel Holten, Hiram Putnam's maternal grandfather, relative to the U.S. Continental Congress from John Avery, James Lovell and Azor Orne, as well as copies (or drafts) of Holten's letters to Richard Henry Less, Col. Enoch Putnam, Dr. A. Putnam, William Carmichael, Moody Spofford and Azor Orne.
This collection is organized into four series:
I. SAMUEL HOLTEN LETTERS, 1780-1796
II. HIRAM AND ELIZABETH PUTNAM LETTERS, 1800-1856
III. BUSINESS PAPERS AND MISCELLANEOUS ITEMS, 1813-1874
IV. DUDLEY P. AND LUCY PHELPS PAPERS, 1852-1885
Information on Use
Terms of Access and Use
The collection is open to research according to the regulations of the Mortimer Rare Book Room.
History of the Collection
The Hiram Putnam Papers were donated to Smith College in 1952 by Wilhelmina Phelps, granddaughter of Hiram Putnam.
Search Terms
Putnam, Hiram; Putnam, Elizabeth O., d. 1848; Holten, Samuel, 1738-1816; Phelps, Dudley Post, 1817-1880; Phelps, Lucy, 1826-1907; Phelps family; China (Ship); Education--New York (State)--Syracuse; Shipping--Massachusetts; Shipping--United States; Massachusetts--Commerce; Massachusetts--Commerce--China; China--Commerce--Massachusetts; United States--History--Constitutional period, 1789-1809--Sources; Account books; Bills of lading; Genealogies.; Ships' papers.; Phelps, Lucy, 1826-1907; Phelps, Dudley Post, 1817-1880; Putnam, Elizabeth O., d. 1848; Avery, John, 1739-1806; Lovell, James, 1737-1814; Orne, Azor, 1731-1796
Additional Information
Related Material
Joseph Peabody papers at the Philips Library, Peabody Essex Museum, Salem, Mass
- Series I. SAMUEL HOLTEN LETTERS 1780-1796, 3 linear inches
  Consists of letters to Samuel Holten and copies of his letters to others involved in the U.S. Continental Congress, arranged in chronological order.
- Series II. HIRAM AND ELIZABETH PUTNAM LETTERS 1800-1856, 3 linear inches
  Consists of letters written and received by Hiram and Elizabeth Putnam, arranged in chronological order.
- Series III. BUSINESS PAPERS AND MISCELLANEOUS ITEMS 1813-1874, 3 linear inches
  Consists of business documents, receipts, accounts and other items related to Hiram Putnam's business interests as a ship's captain involved with South American and China trade and as a businessman in Syracuse, N.Y. Also included are memorial items related to Hiram and Elizabeth Putnam. Arranged in chronological order.
- Series IV. DUDLEY P. AND LUCY PHELPS PAPERS 1852-1885, 3 linear inches
  Consists of some letters between Dudley P. and Lucy Phelps (in chronological order), poetry (manuscript and published) written by Dudley Phelps (in chronological order) and other miscellaneous items and his Phelps family genealogical work (in chronological order).
- Series I. SAMUEL HOLTEN LETTERS 1780-1796
  - Letter from John Avery to Samuel Holton, [Boston, Mass.] 1780 Oct 27., 1 p. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Letter from James Lovell to Samuel Holton 1781 May 22., 1 p. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Letter from J. Lwanurck to Samuel Holton, Philadelphia, Pa. 1783 Jul 16., 1 p. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Copy of letter from Samuel Holton to Col. Pickening, Trenton, N.J. 1784 Dec 4., 1 p. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Copy of letter from Samuel Holton to Col. Hutchinson, New York 1785 Aug 22., 1 p. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Copy of letter from Samuel Holton to Governor [James] Bowdoin, New York 1785 Sep 5., 1 p. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Copy of letter from Samuel Holton to Rich[ard] Henry Lee, New York 1785 Sep 8., 1 p. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Letter from John Avery to Samuel Holton, Boston, Mass. 1785 Sep 20., 4 p. (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Copy of letter from Samuel Holton to Col. Enoch Putnam, New York 1785 Oct 3., 1 p. (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Copy of letter from Samuel Holton to Wm. Carmichael, New York 1785 Nov 1785., 1 p. (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Copy of letter from Samuel Holton to Moody Spofford 1789 Oct 5. (Contains numerous notes related to the administrating of an oath of allegiance to the United States.), 2 p. (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Letter to Samuel Holten from Azor Orne, Boston, Mass. 1795 Feb 14., 1 p. (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Copy of letter from Samuel Holten to Dr. A. Putnam 1796 Aug 27., 1 p. (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Series II. HIRAM AND ELIZABETH PUTNAM LETTERS 1800-1856
  - Letter to Elizabeth Osgood from George Osgood, Andover, Mass. 1800 Sep 16., 3 p. (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Letter to Elizabeth Osgood from George Osgood, Andover, Mass. 1820 Sep 19., 1 p. (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Letter to Hiram Putnam from Elizabeth Putnam, Salem, Mass. 1823 Sep 26, with note from Maria Osgood., 2 p. (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Letter to Baboo Ramshander Mitse from Hiram Putnam, Canton, [China] 1827 Feb 21., 2 p. (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Letter to Hiram Putnam from Jos. Peabody and J. A. Peabody, Salem, Mass. 1827 Apr 13., 2 p. (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Letter (quadruplicate) to Hiram Putnam from Jos. Peabody and J. A. Peabody, Salem, Mass. 1827 Apr 13., 2 p. (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Letter (5.plicate) to Hiram Putnam from Jos. Peabody and J. A. Peabody, Salem, Mass. 1827 Apr 13., 2 p. (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Letter to Hiram Putnam from Elizabeth O. Putnam, Salem, Mass. 1827 Apr 29., 3 p. (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Letter to Hiram Putnam from Elizabeth O. Putnam, Salem, Mass. 1827 May 13., 2 p. (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Letter to Mary Elizabeth Putnam from Hiram Putnam, Lima, Peru 1827 Sep 10., 1 p. (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Letter to Hiram Putnam from [illegible signature], Gungh, India 1827 Sep 15., 3 p. (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Letter to Elizabeth O. Putnam from Hiram Putnam, Lima, Peru 1827 Sep 17., 3 p. (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Letter to Hiram Putnam from [illegible signature], Gungh, India 1827 Oct 2., 2 p. (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Letter to Hiram Putnam from Tho. R. Eldredge, Lima, Peru 1827 Nov 23., 1 p. (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Letter to Rupell & Co., Canton, from Hiram Putnam, Lima, Peru 1827 Nov 30., 1 p. (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Letter to Hiram Putnam from Dan. W. Coit, Lima, Peru 1827 Dec 14., 2 p. (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Letter to Hiram Putnam from [illegible signature], Gungh, India 1828 Jan 15., 1 p. (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Letter to Hiram Putnam from D. W. Coit, Lima, Peru 1828 Jan 18., 2 p. (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Letter to Hiram Putnam from Nixon, Aristia & Co., Copiapo, Chile 1828 Jan 23., 1 p. (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Letter to Hiram Putnam from Dan. W. Coit, Lima, Peru 1828 Jan 24., 2 p. (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Letter to D. W. Coit from Hiram Putnam, Valparaiso, Chile 1828 Jan 24., 2 p. (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Letter to H. Putnam from D. W. Coit, undated. The letter begins with a listing: Mim. of Articles recommended for Capt. Putnam's investment., 3 p. (Box 1, Folder 34a)
  - Letter to Hiram Putnam from [illegible signature], Copiapo, Chile 1828 Feb 11., 2 p. (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Letter to Hiram Putnam from Alsop, Wetmore & Co., Lima, Peru 1828 Apr 14., 1 p. (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Letter to [Hiram Putnam] from [Philmon Putnam], Salem, Mass. 1828 Nov 13., 3 p. (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Letter to Hiram Putnam from Philmon Putnam, Franconia, N. H. 1829 Jan 18., 3 p. (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Letter to Hiram Putnam from Philmon Putnam, Franconia, N. H. 1829 Apr 22., 3 p. (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Letter to Hiram Putnam from Philmon Putnam, Franconia, N. H. 1829 May 2., 1 p. (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Letter to Hiram Putnam from Mary Elizabeth [Putnam], [Salem, Mass.] 1829 Sep 16. Also contains letter to Lucy Putnam and Elizabeth O. Putnam from Mary Elizabeth. Also a letter to Hiram Putnam from E. A. Holyoke., 3 p. (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Copy of letter to J. Chadwick from Hiram Putnam, Syracuse, N.Y. 1829 Oct 29., 1 p. (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Copy of letter to Jno. Chadwick from Hiram Putnam, Syracuse, N.Y. 1829 Nov 25., 1 p. (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Letter to E. A. Holyoke from Hiram Putnam, Syracuse, N.Y. 1830 Jan 18., 2 p. (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Copy of letter to "My dear friend" from Hiram Putnam, Syracuse, N.Y. 1848 Jul 28., 2 p. (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Copy of letter to "My dear friend" from Hiram Putnam, [Syracuse, N.Y. 1848 Aug ?]., 2 p. (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Copy of letter to "My dear sister" [Mrs. Holyoke] from Hiram Putnam, Syracuse, N.Y. 1848 Aug., 3 p. (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Copy of letter to "My dear brother" from Hiram Putnam, Syracuse, N.Y. 1848 Aug 5., 4 p. (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Copy of letter to Mrs. Redfield from [Hiram Putnam], Syracuse, N.Y. 1848 Oct 23., 1 p., incomplete. (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Letter to Hiram Putnam from John Perkins, Utica, N.Y. 1849 Oct 18., 1 p. and envelope. (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - Letter to Capt. Putnam from Amelia Bradbury, Syracuse, N.Y. 1850 Jul 3., 1 p. (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - Letter to H. Putnam from D. Caverno Allen, Syracuse, N.Y. 1850 Jul 9., 1 p. (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - Petition to H. Putnam from "Teacher's in your employ," Syracuse, N.Y. 1850 Jul 31., 1 p. (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - Letter to H. Putnam from H. G. Salisbury, Syracuse, N.Y. 1850 Aug 1., 1 p. (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - Letter to H. Putnam from D. Caverno Allen, Syracuse, N.Y. 1850 Aug 2., 1 p. and envelope. (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - Letter to H. Putnam from Hevoce Eveely, New York 1855 Feb 7., 2 p. (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - Letter to Hiram Putnam from J. B. Brigham, Syracuse, N.H. 1858 Jun 11., 2 p. (Box 1, Folder 57)
  - Letter to "My Dear Sir" [H. Putnam?] from … Beecher, New York 1857 Dec 11., 4 p. (Box 1, Folder 58)
  - Letter to Hiram Putnam from M. L. Classundated, 1 p. and envelope. (Box 1, Folder 59)
  - Letter to "My Dear Friend" [H. Putnam?] from Sam. J. May, Syracuse, N.Y. 1856 Apr 6., 8 p. (Box 1, Folder 60)
  - Envelopes (3) addressed to Hiram Putnam, n.y.Feb. 6-Aug. 2. (Box 1, Folder 61)
  - Poemundated Signed Mary E. Putnam, in another hand than the draft of the poem. Poem begins: How beautifully be these stainless leaves, 2 p. (Box 1, Folder 62)
- Series III. BUSINESS PAPERS AND MISCELLANEOUS ITEMS 1813-1874
  - Account book of Hiram Putnam 1813-1816. The book has the date 1813 on the cover, with entries for 1815-1816, related to the Brig Alice. Includes copies of letters sent by Hiram Putnam., 1 book (Box 1, Folder 63)
  - Prix-courant, Chez Vallée avitailleur de navires … = Price-current, by Vallée ship-chandler … á Anvers. 1818 Jun. 1, 1 p. (Box 1, Folder 63a)
  - Price-current by Valléeundated, 1 p. (Box 1, Folder 63b)
  - Sample "Spanish floret paper", 1 item (Box 1, Folder 63c)
  - Business cards, 181u-182u., 9 cards from Antwerp, 7 cards from other places (Box 1, Folder 63d)
  - "We take the liberty of informing you," Valparaiso, [Chile] 1824 May 1, signed: Fermin Rejo and Herny Dubern., 1 p. (Box 1, Folder 64)
  - Exports to the United States [likely from Canton]. Seasons 1823/1824-1825/1826. Exports from hence to Europe, American vessels. Seasons 1823/24-1825/1826. English East India Company, sent hence to Quebec & Halifax in their ships, season of 1825/1826. Imports into Canton, season 1825/26 from the Unites States, Europe &c. in American vessels.1823-1826, 1 p. (Box 1, Folder 65)
  - Receipt, Capt. Putnam to Thomas Oliver 1826 Oct 28-Nov 5., 2 p. (Box 1, Folder 66)
  - Receipt, Capt. Putnam to Thomas Oliver 1826 Nov 6-Nov 28., 1 p. (Box 1, Folder 67)
  - Consuls bill, Captain Hiram Putnam, owner of the Ship China, to the United States Consulate, Valparaiso, [Chile] 1826 Oct 2., 1 p. (Box 1, Folder 68)
  - Ship China bill, Capt. Putnam of Ship China, Valparaiso, [Chile] 1827 Jun 24., 2 p. (Box 1, Folder 69)
  - Capt. Hiram Putnam in account current with Russell & Co. 1826-1827., 2 p. (Box 1, Folder 70)
  - Cargo of Ship Lord Amherst for Halifax 1827 Jan 6; cargo of Ship Asia for Quebec, Jan 11; cargo of Ship Ann & Amelia for Quebec, Jan 16., 1 p. (Box 1, Folder 71)
  - "Shipped in good order and well conditioned, by Hiram Putnam on board the Ship China …" 1827 May 1., 1 p. (Box 1, Folder 72)
  - "Shipped in good order and well-conditioned, by Russell & Co. on board the Ship called the China …" 1827 May 1., 4 items (Box 1, Folder 73)
  - Promissory note with New-England Marine Insurance Company, signed: Philemon Putnam, Ves'l. China, Boston 1817 May 15., 2 p. (Box 1, Folder 74)
  - "Contract between Messrs. Lewell & Patrickson and Frederick Huth, Coit Co. for twelve hundred quintals of cooper," Valparaiso, [Chile] 1827 Nov 27., 1 p. (Box 1, Folder 75)
  - Price current … Lima, [Peru] 1828 Jan 23., 1 p. (Box 1, Folder 76)
  - Memorandum for China articles for Valparaiso 1828 Jan 29., 4 p. (Box 1, Folder 77)
  - Memorandum for a cargo from W. L. for Chile 1828 Jan 31., 3 p. (Box 1, Folder 78)
  - Receipt, Capt. H. Putnam to Mixon, Austin & Co. 1828 Mar 2., 1 p. (Box 1, Folder 79)
  - Sales of sundry merchandise … from Ship China, Valparaiso, [Chile] 1828 Mar 10., 4 p. (Box 1, Folder 80)
  - Contract between Messrs. Nixon Aristia & Co. and Messrs. Fred. Huth, Coit & Co. for 2500 qgts. of copper 1828 Mar 15., 2 p. (Box 1, Folder 81)
  - Notice on expiration of partnership, between Frederick Huth & Co. and Daniel W. Coit, Lima and London 1828 Apr 12., 2 p. (Box 1, Folder 82)
  - Bill of sale, Capt. Putnam, Ship China, brought of Brig Melville, Callao 1828 Apr 24., 1 p. (Box 1, Folder 83)
  - Bill, Capt. Putnam (Ship China), Callao 1828 Apr 29., 1 p. (Box 1, Folder 84)
  - Document 1828 May 14., 1 p. (Box 2, Folder 85)
  - Receipt between Hiram Putnam and M. Vidaurre, Salem, [Mass.] 1828 Jul 25., 1 p. (Box 2, Folder 86)
  - Receipt, Salem, [Mass.] 1828 Aug 5., 1 p. (Box 2, Folder 87)
  - Receipt to John Holman, for water, Salem, Mass. 1828 Nov 1., 1 p. (Box 2, Folder 87a)
  - Capt. Hiram Putnam in a/c current with Joseph Peabody, Salem, [Mass.] 1829 Jan 7., 2 p. (Box 2, Folder 88)
  - Receipt, Mrs. H. Putnam to Lucy G. Haraden 1829 Jan 29., 1 p. (Box 2, Folder 89)
  - P. Putnam in acct with H. Putnam 1829 Jul., 1 p. (Box 2, Folder 90)
  - Miscellaneous documents related to ships tradeundated, 6 items (Box 2, Folder 91)
  - Account book of Hiram Putnam, [1830] Inventory of household goods and their value, notes cost of shipment to Syracuse, N.Y., lists of assets and property held 1830 Jan 1., 1 book (Box 2, Folder 92)
  - Deed of Henry Gifford to Hiram Putman, Syracuse, N.Y. 1834 Apr 28., 1 item (Box 2, Folder 93)
  - Deed to Hiram Putnam, cemetery plot 1842 Jun 22., 1 item (Box 2, Folder 94)
  - Documents on salt water in Syracuse, N.Y., n.d, 3 items (Box 2, Folder 95)
  - The sermon preached in the Church of the Messiah, Syracuse, the Sunday after the death of Elizabeth O. Putnam, by S. J. M. [Samuel Joseph May], [the Church of the Messiah was later called the May Memorial Unitarian Church] 1848 Jul 30.1, 8 p. (Box 2, Folder 96)
  - Obituary of Elizabeth O. Putnam, the Daily Journal, Syracuse, N.Y. 1848 Aug 3., 1 p. (Box 2, Folder 97)
  - Receipt - Washington National Monument Office 1849 Dec. 1, 1 p. (Box 2, Folder 98)
  - Offprints on education 1850., 2 items (Box 2, Folder 99)
  - Hiram Putnam [memorial book] 1874., cop. 1, with Putnam portrait. (Box 2, Folder 100)
  - Hiram Putnam [memorial book] 1874., cop. 2, lacking Putnam portrait. (Box 2, Folder 101)
- Series IV. DUDLEY P. AND LUCY PHELPS PAPERS 1852-1885
  - Letters
    - Letter (copy) from Dudley P. Phelps to Theo. Parker and reply, Boston 1852 Feb 1.7, 1 p. (Box 2, Folder 102)
    - Letter to Dudley P. Phelps from Theo. Parker, Boston 1852 Feb 6., 8 p. and envelope (Box 2, Folder 103)
    - Letter to Lucy Phelps from Dudley P. Phelps, Adrian, Mich. 1856 Oct. 5., 4 p. and envelope (Box 2, Folder 104)
    - Letter to Dudley P. Phelps from Lewis L., Philadelphia 1858 Dec 3., 3 p. (Box 2, Folder 105)
    - Letter to "Treasurer of the Unitarian Society in Syracuse, N. Y.," [Dudley P. Phelps from Henry W. Bellows, New York 1858 Dec 19., 4 p. and envelope (Box 2, Folder 106)
    - Letter to "My Dear Wifey" [Lucy Phelps from Dudley P. Phelps], Toledo, Ohio 1859 Apr 3, incomplete., 4 p. (Box 2, Folder 107)
    - Letter to Mr. May from L. S. Parker, Boston 1862 Nov 26, followed by letter to "Dear Friend" from Saml J. May, Syracuse, N.Y., [1862] Nov 28., 4 p. (Box 2, Folder 108)
    - Letter to Dudley P. Phelps from L. S. Parker, Boston 1862 Dec 12., 2 p. and envelope (Box 2, Folder 109)
    - Letter to Mr. & Mrs. D. P. Phelps from Samuel J. May, Winthrop, Mass. 1870 Aug 31., 4 p. and envelope (Box 2, Folder 110)
    - Letter to D. P. Phelps from John G. Whittier, Amesbury, Mass. 1875 Sep 21., 2 p. (Box 2, Folder 111)
    - Letter to "My Dear Cousin Lucy" [Phelps] from G. Osgood, Kensington, N.H. 1888 Jun 14., 4 p. (Box 2, Folder 112)
    - Letter (fragment) to [Lucy Phelps] from Dudley [Phelps]undated, 1 p. (Box 2, Folder 113)
  - Poems
    - Dudley P. Phelps. Poem, Christmas Eve 1843. First line read: Kind greetings to you all good neighbors, friends., 8 p. (Box 2, Folder 114)
    - Dudley P. Phelps. Poem, Valentine's Day, Syracuse 1844. First line reads: From the realms of Queen Mab, came a troupe last night., 2 p. (Box 2, Folder 115)
    - Dudley P. Phelps. Poem: The Rescue of Terry. Syracuse 1852 Oct 1, the day of the County Fair and of a State Anti-Slavery Convention. 1858., 2 p. (Box 2, Folder 116)
    - Dudley P. Phelps. Poem: To my Wifey. Adrian, Mich. 1856 Oct 12., 3 p. and 3 p. of preliminary draft. (Box 2, Folder 117)
    - Dudley P. Phelps. Poem. Read at annual meeting, Cicero 1872 Jan 24. First line reads: A crystal lake with island gemmed., 3 p. (Box 2, Folder 118)
    - Phelps, Dudley P. The Bar of Onondaga: a Poem Read at the Annual Supper of the Onondaga County Bar Association, January 14th, 1879. Syracuse, N.Y.: Davis, Bardeen & Co.1879., 16 p.; 17 cm. (Box 2, Folder 119)
    - Dudley P. Phelps. Poem (draft). undated First line reads: A Merry Christmas to all people., 3 p. and 2 p. of preliminary draft. (Box 2, Folder 120)
    - Dudley P. Phelps. Poem (incomplete?). undated, 1 p. and envelope (Box 2, Folder 121)
  - Miscellaneous
    - Autographs cut from letters: Ls. Agassiz, William H. Seward, Edw. E. Hale and newspaper clipping., 4 items (Box 2, Folder 122)
    - Deposit slips of Lucy B. Phelps in the Trust and Deposit Company of Onondaga, Syracuse, N.Y. 1904 Jul 19; 1904 Sep 21., 2 items (Box 2, Folder 123)
    - Puzzles and trivia games., 8 items (Box 2, Folder 124)
    - Phelps, Dudley P. A Genealogical Record of the Descendants of Joseph and Jemima (Post) Phelps, of Hebron, Connecticut … Syracuse, N.Y. 1885. [This copy has a few annotations and text corrections. Cover title: The Phelps Record.], 96 p.; 24 cm. (Box 2, Folder 125)
    - Miscellaneous papers previously laid-in the above copy., 11 items (Box 2, Folder 126)
    - Phelps, Dudley P. A Genealogical Record of the Descendants of Joseph and Jemima (Post) Phelps, of Hebron, Connecticut … Syracuse, N.Y. 1885. This copy has annotated additions to the text. Cover title: The Phelps Record., 96 p.; 24 cm. (Box 2, Folder 127)
    - Day, Fanny Williams. Daymycoglyphs: A New Art on the Fungus Growth with Details and Instructions. Utica, N.Y. 1922.Previously laid in the above copy of The Phelps Record., 11 p.; 24 cm. (Box 2, Folder 128)